Preliminary Guide to the Irvin Family Papers, circa 1890s-2016 RL.00619
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Irvin Family papers
circa 1890s-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Irvin family
RL.00619
10.25 Linear Feet 23 boxes; 2 oversize folders
Collection consists largely of correspondence between historian Nell Irvin Painter and her parents (1969-2003), documenting various stages of their lives, travels, and Painter's scholarly career. Also includes writings by or about Nell Painter, including reviews of her work; materials, including photographs and tintypes (circa 1890s-1910s) of African Americans in Victoria, Texas, kept by Frank and Dona Irvin, relating to their early life near Houston, and documenting aspects of African American history in that area; copies and reviews of Dona Irvin's writings; documents related to Frank and Dona's education and careers; family photographs; videos; Frank irvin's diary (2000-2003); legal papers; and other items. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
approximately 5150 Items
Biographical Note
Dona Irvin (1917-2009) was the author of The Unsung Heart of Black America, I Hope I Look That Good When I'm That Old, and other works. Frank Irvin was a chemist and worked for many years for the Chemistry Department of the University of California at Berkeley. The Irvins are the parents of historian Nell Irvin Painter, whose papers are also in the Rubenstein Library.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Irvin Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2003, 2015, 2016, and 2019.
Related Material
For more information, see the Nell Irvin Painter Papers, 1959-2002 and undated, in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
Collection consists largely of correspondence between historian Nell Irvin Painter and her parents (1969-2003), documenting various stages of their lives, travels, and Painter's scholarly career. Also includes writings by or about Nell Painter, including reviews of her work; copies and reviews of Dona Irvin's writings; documents related to Frank and Dona's education and careers; Frank irvin's diary (2000-2003); legal papers; and other items.
Photographs also form an important part of the collection. Along with papers and records, Frank and Dona Irvin kept early photos and tintypes (circa 1890s-1910s) of African Americans in Victoria, Texas; together, these materials speak to their early life near Houston, and document aspects of African American history in that area. There are also family photographs from later decades (1930s-1980s).
For preservation purposes, original audiovisual media are closed to use; copies may be available on request.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
African American families; African American families -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- Professional education; African Americans -- History -- 19th century; African Americans -- Texas -- History; African Americans -- Employment; African Americans -- Correspondence; African Americans -- Photographs; College teachers -- Correspondence; Scholars -- Correspondence; Victoria (Tex.) -- History; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Diaries; Tintypes (prints); Videocassettes; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Irvin family; Painter, Nell Irvin; Irvin, Dona L., 1917-; Irvin, Frank
- Accession 2003-0185
  - Irvin Family
    - Awards (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Frank's Plaques and Certificates.
    - Correspondence, [1983-2001] (Box 1)
    - Family Photographs (Box 2)
    - Legal Papers (Box 2)
      Real Estate and Title Documents, [1960-1988]
    - Correspondence, [1977-1989] (Box 3)
      Includes letters to Dona from Frank.
    - Happily Ever After: Couples Talk About Lasting Love (Box 3)
      Featuring interview with Frank and Dona Irvin.
    - Dona's College Records (Box 3)
      Includes records from Prairie View College, Houston College for Negroes (now Texas Southern), and UCB.
    - Black Women Stirring the Waters, reviews and excerpts (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, [1995-1996] (Box 4)
    - Books Written by Dona Irvin
      - Black Women Stirring the Waters (Box 4)
      - The Unsung Heart of Black America: A Middleclass Church at Midcentury (Box 4)
      - I Hope I Look That Good When I'm That Old: An Older African-American Woman Speaks to All Women in All of America (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1984-1993 (Box 5)
    - Photos of Ewart and Charles E. McGruder (Box 5)
    - Prairie View: A Study in Public Conscience (Box 5)
      The narrative by George Ruble Woolfolk is the story of the only state-supported Negro college in Texas between 1878 and 1946.
  - Nell Irvin Painter
    - Correspondence, 1969-2003 (Box 6-12)
      Includes letters from Nell Irvin Painter to her parents.
    - Articles and Reviews by and About Nell Irvin Painter, 1968-2001 (Box 13)
      Includes articles and publicity about Sojourner Truth, a Life, a Symbol
    - Writing by Nell Irvin Painter 1970 (Box 13)
      Jim Crow at Harvard, 1923
    - Commencement Programs
      - Yale University 2003 (Box 13)
      - Dartmouth College 1997 (Box 13)
      - Wesleyan University 1996 (Box 13)
      - Princeton University 1996 (Box 13)
    - Videos
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual media closed to use. Listening or viewing copies may be available upon request. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
      - MacNeil/Lehrer News with Nell Irvin Painter 1991 Mar. 13 (Box 14)
      - C-SPAN (Box 14)
        Nell Irvin Painter talks about her book Sojourner Truth: A Life, A Symbol
      - Book Notes from Sojourner Truth: A Life, A Symbol 1996 Dec. 8 (Box 14)
      - C-SPAN Organization of American Historians. The Art of Writing 2002 Mar. 13 (Box 14)
    - Assorted Photographs (Box 14)
      Includes photographs from Nell and Glenn's wedding and the OBU rally at Harvard.
    - Assorted Photographs and Postcards (Box 15)
      Includes Nell Irvin Painter's high school photographs, photographs from trip to Quebec City, 2001, and portraits and tintypes taken in Victoria, Texas, ca. 1890s-1900s.
    - Nell's Home in North Carolina (Box 15)
    - Family Photographs (Box 16)
      Includes black-and-white photos, [1930s]-[1980s]
    - Correspondence, 1995-2003 (Box 16)
      Includes e-mail messages from Nell Irvin Painter to her parents.
    - High School Diploma and Graduation Ceremony, 1959 (Box 17)
    - Pelican Magazine UCB, 1959 (Box 17)
    - Harvard Union Commencement Program, 1974 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 17)
      Includes Nell Irvin Painter's letters to her parents.
    - Photographs (Box 18)
      Includes pictures from Crossroads Africa summer in Nigeria.
    - Legal Papers, 1945 (Box 18)
    - Documents Regarding Nell Irvin Painter's Education
      - Education Abroad Program, Boreaux, France, 1962 (Box 18)
      - B.A. from UCB, 1964 (Box 18)
      - M.A. from UCLA, 1967 (Box 18)
      - CA Junior College Teaching Credential, Life. 1968 (Box 18)
      - Nell Irvin Painter curriculum vitae. 1984 (Box 18)
- Accession 2015-0035
  - Frank Irvin's Diary, 2000-2003 (Box 19)
  - Books Written by Dona Irvin
    - Expenses for The Unsung Heart of Black America
    - Book Reviews: The Unsung Heart of Black America (Box 19)
    - Drafts (Box 19)
    - Drafts - I Hope I Look That Good When I'm That Old (Box 19)
    - Correspondence - I Hope I Look That Good When I'm That Old (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 19)
    Scope and Contents
    Largely correspondence between Nell Irvin Painter and her parents, ranging from the 1960s to 2000s. Includes email correspondence.
  - Photographs (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 19)
  - Biographical essay - Dona Irvin (Box 20)
  - Events (Box 20)
    Includes planning materials for Frank Irvin's 85th birthday party and materials from memorial services, including Dona Irvin's memorial service.
  - Printed Material (Box 20)
  - Awards (Box 20)
    Includes Frank Irvin's Certificate of Appreciation for 25 years of service from the Univerisity of California.
  - Medical Documents (Box 20)
  - Legal and Financial documents (Box 20)
    Includes photocopies of Frank and Dona Irvin's marriage certificate, tax records, and talent release forms.
  - Photocopies - Research Material (Box 20)
  - Clippings (Box 20)
  - AV Materials (Box 20)
    Original audiovisual media closed to use. Listening or viewing copies may be available on request. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
- Accession 2015-0192
  - Correspondence, 2007-2009 (Box 21)
  - Frank and Dona Irvin's Wedding Anniversary Guest Book, 1997 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence received by Frank Irvin, 2009-2011; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Dona Irvin correspondence and notes, 2007 (Box 21)
  - Dona Irvin obituary, 2009 (Box 21)
  - Family photographs, 1985, 1997, and undated (Box 21, Oversize-folder 1)
- Accession 2016-0112
  Addition (2016-0112) contains materials transferred from the Nell Irvin Painter papers. Contains family photographs primarily from the 1990s and a calendar in which Dona and Frank Irvin appeared.
  - Photograph of Frank and Dona Irvin at Dona's retirement party, 1982 (Box 22)
  - Portrait of Dona and Nell taken by Bill Gaskins, ca. 1999 (Box 22)
  - Family snapshots 1964-1999 and undated (Box 22)
  - 2002 calendar:Happily Ever After, pictures of everlasting love (Oversize-folder 2)
    Month of April features a portrait of Dona and Frank Irvin.
- Accession 2019-0101
  - Donna Irvin's memorial service, 2009 (Box 23)
  - General correspondence, 2011-2017 (Box 23)
  - McGruder family correspondence, 2016-2018 (Box 23)
  - Photographs, 1890s-2014 (Box 23)
  - Frank Irvin's memorial service, 2016 (Box 23)